Patrick Landon Ferree

Medical Museion, Fredericiagade 18, Copenhagen K, Denmark • patrick.ferree@sund.ku.dk • +45 93 86 71 37

Profile

Patrick is a PhD student and researcher at Medical Museion and CBMR. He has a background in philosophy, chemistry, and developmental biology, postdoc experience in exposure science, and is pursuing a PhD in philosophy of science. His work uses qualitative methods (ethnography and interviews) to investigate epistemological and sociocultural dimensions of cell atlases and single-cell methods in the biomedical sciences. *Research areas:* Philosophy of the Biomedical Sciences; Philosophy of Science in Practice; History and Philosophy of Science (&HPS); Science and Technology Studies (STS).

EDUCATION

University of Copenhagen

PhD Student in Philosophy of Science – Program in Medicine, Culture, and Society	in Progress
 Duke University School of Medicine PhD in Developmental Biology - Certificate in Cell and Molecular Biology Dissertation: Temporal regulation of cell divisions in the embryo of Drosophila melanogaster Committee: Stefano Di Talia, Michel Bagnat, Danny Lew, Bernard Mathey-Prevot, Nick Buchler 	Durham, NC, USA Apr 2022
University of California, San Diego BA in Philosophy, BS in Chemistry, Minor in Political Science, magna cum laude	La Jolla, CA, USA Jun 2012
Experience	
 University of Copenhagen PhD Student, Advisors: Karin Tybjerg & Sara Green Affiliation: Medical Museion, Department of Public Health, Faculty of Medical and Health Sciences Affiliation: Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for Basic Metabolic Research (CBMR) Affiliation: Center for Medical Science and Technology Studies (MeST) Research: Sociocultural and epistemological dimensions of technologies in biomedical science 	Copenhagen, DK Mar 2024 - Present
The National Research Centre for the Working Environment Postdoctoral Researcher, Advisor: Keld Alstrup Jensen • Research: Occupational exposure to airborne particles	Copenhagen, DK Jun 2022 - Mar 2024
Copenhagen Institute for Futures Studies Intern, Advisor: Bogi Eliasen • Research: Futures of healthcare and biomedicine	Copenhagen, DK Jan - Jun 2022
 Duke University School of Medicine PhD Student, Advisor: Stefano Di Talia Affiliation: Department of Cell Biology Research: Temporal patterning of mitosis in fly embryos 	Durham, NC, USA Sep 2014 - Apr 2022
 University of Texas, El Paso Research Technician, Advisor: Laura O'Dell Affiliation: Department of Psychology Research: Neuroscience of drug addiction in rats 	El Paso, TX, USA Jan 2013 - Sep 2014
Scripps Institute of Oceanography Research Assistant, Advisor: Lynn Russell • Research: Chemistry and physics of atmospheric aerosols	La Jolla, CA, USA Jan - Sep 2012

Copenhagen, DK

PUBLICATIONS

- P. L. Ferree, M. Polat, J. K. Nøjgaard, K. A. Jensen, "Airborne particulate matter and diesel engine exhaust on infrastructure construction sites in the Copenhagen metropolitan area", *Annals of Work Exposures and Health*, Aug. 2024, doi.org/10.1093/annweh/wxae062 (Article).
- P. L. Ferree, M. Xing, J.Q. Zhang, S. Di Talia, "Structure-function analysis of Cdc25 Twine degradation at the Drosophila maternal-to-zygotic transition", Fly, vol. 16, no. 1, pp. 111–117, Dec. 2022, ISSN: 1933-6934 (Article).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Di Talia, "Developmental Biology: Embryos Need to Control Their Nucleotides Just Right", Current Biology, vol. 29, no. 7, R252–R254, Apr. 2019, ISSN: 09609822 (Preview).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Di Talia, "Chemical Waves in Embryonic Cell Cycles", *Israel Journal of Chemistry*, vol. 58, no. 6, pp. 714–721, 2018, ISSN: 18695868 (**Review**).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Di Talia, "For Embryos, Mother Can Only Take You So Far", *Developmental Cell*, vol. 42, no. 3, pp. 203–205, 2017, ISSN: 18781551 (Preview).
- P. L. Ferree, V. Deneke, S. Di Talia, "Measuring time during early embryonic development", Seminars in Cell and Developmental Biology, 2016, ISSN: 10849521 (Review).
- L. M. Carcoba, J. E. Orfila, L. E. Natividad, O. V. Torres, J. A. Pipkin, **P. L. Ferree**, E. Castañeda, D. E. Moss, L. E. O'Dell, "Cholinergic transmission during nicotine withdrawal is influenced by age and pre-exposure to nicotine: Implications for teenage smoking", *Developmental Neuroscience*, vol. 36, no. 3-4, pp. 347–355, 2014, ISSN: 14219859 (Article).
- O. V. Torres, J. A. Pipkin, **P. L. Ferree**, L. M. Carcoba, L. E. O'Dell, "Nicotine withdrawal increases stress-associated genes in the nucleus accumbens of female rats in a hormone-dependent manner", *Nicotine and Tobacco Research*, vol. 17, no. 4, pp. 422–430, 2014, ISSN: 1469994X (**Article**).

Manuscripts in Progress

- P. L. Ferree, C. Ribalta, A. CØ Jensen, A. Brostrøm, T. Berthing, K. A. Jensen, "Airborne nano/microplastics in the plastics recycling and manufacturing industry" (Article In Preparation).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Brantley, T. Starr, A. Chao, S. Di Talia, "Activator-accumulation and repressor-depletion time mitosis during *Drosophila* gastrulation" (Article In Preparation).

Select Talks and Poster Presentations

- P. L. Ferree, "Technical and epistemic objects in cell-type classification: A study of single-cell sequencing", Society for Philosophy of Science in Practice (SPSP), Columbia, SC, USA, May 2024 (Poster).
- P. L. Ferree, C. Ribalta, A. Jensen, J. K. Nøjgaard, S. Nielsen, N. Sahlgren, T. Berthing, K. A. Jensen, "Workplace exposure to ultrafine particles, chemicals, and dust during plastic production with recycled plastics", British Occupational Hygiene Society: Inhaled Particles and NanOEH, Manchester, UK, May 2023 (Talk).
- P. L. Ferree, A. De Simone, S. Di Talia, "An activator-repressor model for improved temporal precision of transcription", Quantitative Biology (Q-Bio), Oahu, HI, USA, Feb 2019 (Talk).
- P. L. Ferree, C. Bunce, "The Questions of Developmental Biology", The Society for Developmental Biology (SDB), Boston, MA, USA, Jul 2019 (Poster).
- P. L. Ferree, A. De Simone, S. Di Talia, "An activator-repressor model for improved temporal precision of transcription", Tissue Self-Organization: Challenging the Systems, Heidelberg, Germany, Mar 2018 (Poster).

SELECT SCHOOLS AND WORKSHOPS ATTENDED AS A STUDENT

Diagnosis Conference: Between Knowing and Doing, Medical Museion, Copenhagen, Oct 2024.

European Advanced School for the Philosophy of the Life Sciences, Konrad Lorenz Institute, Austria, Sep 2024.

Summer School on the History of Knowledge, Lund University (LUCK), Sweden, Aug 2024.

Crossing the Disciplinary Boundaries of Physics, Bohr Centennial, Copenhagen, Denmark, Aug 2023.

Workshop on Methods in the Philosophy of Science, University of Vienna, Austria, May 2023.

Summer School on the History of the Life Sciences, Ischia, Italy, Jun 2022.

Winter School on Quantitative Biology, International Center for Theoretical Physics, Trieste, Italy, Dec 2017.

ACADEMIC SOCIETIES

Member, Society for Philosophy of Science in Practice (SPSP), 2023-present.

Member, Society for Social Studies of Science (4S), 2024-present.

Member, International Society for the History, Philosophy, and Social Studies of Biology (ISHPSSB), 2024-present.

Member, Philosophy of Science Association (PSA), 2024-present.

Member, History of Science Society (HSS), 2024-present.

SERVICE TO THE COMMUNITY

Member of Editorial Team, Society for Philosophy of Science in Practice Newsletter, 2024-present.

References

Karin Tybjerg, PhD

Associate Professor, Medical Museion and CBMR, University of Copenhagen

Email: karin.tybjerg@sund.ku.dk, Phone: +45 35 32 38 03

Sara Green, PhD

Associate Professor, History and Philosophy of Science, University of Copenhagen

Email: sara.green@ind.ku.dk, Phone: $+45\ 35\ 33\ 46\ 32$

Keld Alstrup Jensen, PhD

Professor, Chemistry and Microbiology, National Research Centre for the Working Environment

Email: kaj@nfa.dk, Phone: +45 20 76 47 31

Stefano Di Talia, PhD

Associate Professor, Department of Cell Biology, Duke University

Email: stefano.ditalia@duke.edu, Phone: +1 919 684 8079